A Guide to the Papers of Alice Jackson Stuart, 1913-2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Alice Jackson Stuart 1913-2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12512
This collection consists of ca. 19,200 items (64 Hollinger boxes, ca. 26.5 linear shelf feet), ca. 1930-2001, and some printed material from the nineteenth century.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Judge Julian Towns Houston, Brookline, Massachusetts, on April 24, 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
Alice Carlotta Jackson was born on June 2, 1913, above her father's pharmacy, in Richmond, Virginia, to James Edward Jackson, Sr. (1879-1957) and Clara Louise Kersey Jackson (1886-1960). During her elementary and high school years, she attended the Hartshorn Memorial College (1919-1930), which operated from 1883 until 1930, when the elementary and high school programs were eliminated and the college department merged with Virginia Union University. It was located on the site of present day Maggie L. Walker High School in Richmond, Virginia.
Jackson received her Bachelor of Arts degree from Virginia Union University in 1934 and her Master of Arts degree from Columbia University in 1939, with her thesis "Literary Criticism in John Milton's Prose Works." For a draft of her thesis see Box 22 of this collection.
In addition she attended the following workshops: Psychology at Howard University (1948); Speech for Classroom Teachers, Virginia Commonwealth University (1951); Fellow Fund for Advancement of Education, Ford Foundation (1953-1954), where she traveled, studied, and participated in productions for Mass Media in Education at Teacher's College, Columbia University and the University of Southern California; Rutgers Workshop for High School Teachers of English (1959); Fairleigh Dickenson University - Poetry Society of America Creative Writing Workshop (1963); and a Casenovia College NEH Workshop on Resources for Teaching Literature of Black America (1969). She also received a National Endowment for the Humanities grant in 1981 for a research project. Files with information about most of these post graduate education and enrichment opportunities can be found in Series IV: Subject and Topical Files.
Alice Jackson had applied to the University of Virginia graduate school in 1935 and was the first known African-American to seek admission into a Virginia state graduate or professional school. Her application was rejected by the University of Virginia because of her race and for "other good and sufficient reasons" not spelled out in correspondence between the University and Alice Jackson (copies of this correspondence and related material can be found in Box 54). As a result of her application, the Virginia General Assembly established a tuition supplement fund for minority students who wanted to attend graduate and professional schools out of state. This legislation was worked out by the Virginia Commission on Interracial Cooperation to provide a tuition supplement that would compensate for the difference in cost for attending an out-of-state school.
The teaching experience of Alice Jackson Stuart included work at Virginia Union University (1935-1936); teaching French at what is now Norfolk State College (1936-1937); Bethune-Cookman College (1938-1942); Howard University (1944-1950); English for Nurses at the Medical College of Virginia (1951-1953); Virginia Public Schools in Richmond at Armstrong High School and Maggie L. Walker High School (1951-1959); Rutgers State University, Douglass College (1960-1963); and at Middlesex County College from 1966 until her retirement, in 1983, as professor of English.
In addition to her educational work, she also was occasionally employed part-time writing for Ebony-Jet, Afro-American Newspapers in Richmond, Virginia, Journal and Guide Weekly, and as a columnist for Virginia Today, 1951-1953. From 1964-1966, Stuart worked as an educational research specialist for the ITT - Federal Electric Company Kilmer Job Corps Center in New Jersey (Boxes 38-39). Stuart was a member of the Delta Sigma Theta Sorority and a charter member of Delta Sigma Theta at Virginia Union University. Material related to her long membership in the Delta Sigma Sorority is present in Boxes 12-14.
Alice Jackson Stuart was married first to Julian Towns Houston, Sr. in April 1940, and they had one son, Julian Towns Houston. Her second marriage was to Dr. James Earle Stuart on November 12, 1960. Files about the career and death of Dr. Stuart can be found in Boxes 18 and 19.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Alice Jackson Houston Stuart (1913-2001), an educator and early Virginia civil rights figure, consist of ca. 19,200 items (64 Hollinger boxes, ca. 26.5 linear shelf feet), ca. 1930-2001, and some printed material from the nineteenth century. The collection includes correspondence, biographical information, topical files, research files, organizational and professional files, original writings by Alice Jackson Stuart and her son, Julian Houston, and papers and photographs pertaining to the career of her second husband, Doctor James Earle Stuart, and his estate.
The correspondence series consists chiefly of personal correspondence with friends and family, invitations to social events, greeting cards, and post cards. Of particular note in the series are letters pertaining to her educational opportunities during her career (Box 1), especially an early letter from Charles Houston, October 13, 1936, advising her about the amount the state of Virginia was offering to pay to enable her to attend Columbia University.
Other notable files include the correspondence of Alice Jackson with her parents, 1935-1939 (Box 5), letters pertaining to her professional career (Box 8), speaking opportunities (Box 9) and a small VIP file of correspondence (Box 9) including: Mary McLeod Bethune, Edward W. Brooke, W.E.B. DuBois (copy only), Michael S. Dukakis, Lena Horne, Robert F. Kennedy, Mrs. Ada MacLeish on behalf of her husband, Archibald MacLeish, Isabel Powell (wife of Adam Clayton Powell), Dan Quayle, Barbara Summers, Mary Church Terrell, and Harrison A. Williams, Jr.
The series on personal and family materials includes Stuart's address and telephone books; calendar and appointment books; all types of biographical and autobiographical information; membership and involvement in the Delta Sigma Theta Sorority; diplomas; news clippings about Stuart; membership cards; obituaries and funeral programs for friends (arranged chronologically) with a separate folder for Spottswood W. Robinson, III; photographs (only a few of Alice Jackson Stuart are present) and slides; plaques, chiefly about membership in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; programs to various events, arranged by type; government resolutions concerning Stuart; various travel folders; and material about Dr. James Earle Stuart.
The third series consist of notes made by Alice Jackson Stuart or completed articles, essays, drafts of her book on the baseball player Don Newcombe, high school and college class papers, her Masters thesis on John Milton, play adaptations, newspapers articles, poetry, speeches, including one at the University of Virginia Office of Afro-American Affairs Honors Banquet, and short stories. The notes are arranged by topic when apparent, and include college course notes, notes for classes she taught, notes about teaching, black history and culture, and other personal interests.
Series four is the largest series and contains subject and topical files. The largest groups of these are concerned with her long career of teaching at the Middlesex County College, Edison, New Jersey, from its beginnings until her retirement (Boxes 39-43); her membership and active roles in the National Council of Teachers of English and the associated Conference on College Composition and Communication, where Stuart served on the Executive committee, 1972-1975 (Boxes 44-47); and Dr. and Mrs. Stuart's public and community service to Plainfield, New Jersey (Boxes 48-50).
Other files reveal her interest in race relations, the arts, black history and culture, various educational issues, civil rights and civil rights organizations, the Democratic Party, membership in the First Unitarian Church of Richmond, Virginia, and Plainfield, New Jersey, social issues, including housing and urban renewal, various museums, human relations, application to the University of Virginia in 1935 (Box 54), L. Douglas Wilder (Box 56), and Virginia Union University (Box 55-56).
Another item of note in series four is the World War II diary and letters, 1943-1944, of a black serviceman, Granver Paige Thomas (1923-?), a member of Company B, 1313th Engineer Regiment, General Service, who was stationed at Fort George E. Meade, on July 24, 1943, and transferred to Camp Claiborne, Louisiana, on August 5, 1943 (see Box 54). The diary describes his basic training in great detail from the time he entered service in July until he was shipped out from Camp Claiborne in January 1944 in preparation of going to England. The letters are from Thomas to his mother, Mrs. Anna V. Cutts, while he was stationed in England in 1944.
The fifth series of educational files and research materials includes bibliographies, syllabi, and files with educational topics, such as curriculum reform, the gifted child, grading, the junior and community college, low income students, the possible impact of television and radio upon education, reading, testing, vocabulary and spelling, and writing and composition, among others.
There are also files of research material about Africa; black artists; blacks in education and medical fields; black history, literature, media, theater, musicians, singers, and other performers; the Caribbean Islands and their literature; the civil rights movement; women's studies; the Civil War, and Richmond.
Research folders on individuals include: Roland Hayes, Langston Hughes, John Keats, Alice Dunbar Nelson and Maggie Lena Walker.
Organization
Much of the printed material that came with the papers but did not relate specifically to Stuart or her professional career was separated and transferred to Rare Books for individual cataloging and handling. Five series were then created based on the type of material present. All material marked as oversize in the box listing are actually stored in oversize boxes separate from the collection. Please ask staff members for assistance in requesting these items.
These papers are arranged in five series, including:
Series I: Correspondence (Boxes 1-9)
Series II: Personal and Family Files (Boxes 9-20)
Series III: Notes and Writings by Alice Jackson Stuart (Boxes 21-30)
Series IV: Subject and Topical Files (Boxes 30-56)
Series V: Educational Files and Research Materials (Boxes 57-64)
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence - Kay Bell Banks 1984-1992, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Church and Social Work 1952-1969, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Disposition of the papers of Alice Jackson 1985-2002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Materials concerning the Dissertation about Alice Jackson Stuart by Larissa Smith at Emory University 1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Education of Alice Jackson, including a letter from Charles H. Houston 1934-1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Former Students 1950-1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - John and Katt Gandy 1986-1990 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Greeting Cards (3 folders) 1940-1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Greeting Cards (6 Folders) 1990-2001 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Greeting Cards (7 Folders) 2000-2001, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Invitations (7 Folders) 1948, 1955-1991 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Invitations (2 Folders) 1992-2001, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence - Alice Jackson with her parents 1935-1939 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence - Personal (7 Folders) 1930-1979 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence - Personal (8 Folders) 1980-1991 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence - Personal (8 Folders) 1992-2001, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - Personal (2 Folders) n.d. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - Post cards (3 Folders) 1931-2001, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - Professional (2 Folders) 1935-1998, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - Helen O. Sims (2 folders) 1984-2000 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - Solicitation Letters and Gift Thank-yous (2 folders) 1959-2000, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - Speaking Opportunities 1958-1998 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - VIP, These include: Mary McLeod Bethune, Edward W. Brooke, W.E.B. DuBois (copy only), Michael S. Dukakis, Lena Horne, Robert F. Kennedy, Mrs. Ada MacLeish on behalf of her husband, Archibald MacLeish, Isabel Powell (wife of Adam Clayton Powell, Dan Quayle, Barbara Summers, Mary Church Terrell, Harrison A. Williams, Jr. 1934-1997 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - P.B. Young, publisher of Journal and Guide1955-1956 (Box 9)
- Series II: Personal and Family Materials (Box 9)
  - Address and Telephone Books (4 volumes and one folder) n.d. (Box 9)
  - Addresses and Phone Numbers - Loose (7 folders) n.d. (Box 10)
  - Autobiographical Writings by Alice Jackson Stuart n.d. (Box 11)
  - Awards 1954-1959, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Biographical Information concerning Alice Jackson Stuart 1982-1999 (Box 11)
  - Biographical Information concerning Alice Jackson Stuart - Interviews 1952, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Biographical Information concerning Alice Jackson Stuart - Memberships and Teaching Certificates 1947-1998 (Box 11)
  - Biographical Information concerning Alice Jackson Stuart -Resumes and Personal Data Sheets ca. 1950-1980 (Box 11)
  - Biographical Information concerning Alice Jackson Stuart - Transcripts from Colleges 1931-1960 (Box 11)
  - Biographical Information concerning the Family of Alice Jackson Stuart 1945-1999, n.d. (Box 11)
  - "Birthday Book" belonging to Alice Jackson 1932 (Box 11)
  - Business Cards n.d. (Box 11)
  - Calendars and Appointment Books (2 folders) 1962-1967, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Calendars and Appointment Books (6 folders) 1973-1999 (Box 12)
  - Class Examinations of Alice Jackson Stuart 1931, 1954, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority 1955-1988 (Box 12)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority (2 folders) 1989-2001, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - Black Women's Political Action Forum 1988 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - Constitution and By-laws 1992, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - "Delta Doings - Worldwide" Script Los Angeles 1954 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - "History of Delta Sigma Theta Sorority" [1935 Jun] (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - KABC Radio "Man of Color" interview with two members, Mrs. Paula Garner Glass and Mrs. Alice Jackson [Houston] Stuart 1954 May (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - Membership Certificate of Alice Jackson 1934 Jan 2 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - The Montclair Alumnae Chapter Roster 1981, 1997-1998 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - "My Sorority A Memory Book" belonging to Alice Carlotta Jackson 1933 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - 40th National Convention Program and Workbook 1990 (Box 13)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority - 42nd through 45th National Convention 1994-2000 (Box 14)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Day at the Virginia General Assembly 1990-1994 (Box 14)
  - Diploma of Alice Carlotta Jackson from Columbia University, New York City (oversize) 1939 Jun 6 (Box 14)
  - Diploma of Alice Carlotta Jackson from Hartshorn Memorial College, Richmond, Virginia (oversize) 1930 Sep 15 (Box 14)
  - Diploma of Alice Carlotta Jackson from Virginia Union University, Richmond, Virginia (oversize) 1934 Jun 5 (Box 14)
  - Essay - "The Woman Who Inspires Me" by Lizzie Houston about her grandmother, Alice Jackson Stuart 1996 Feb 24 (Box 14)
  - Funeral Memorial Book for Alice G. Taylor Stuart (1897-1959) 1959 (Box 14)
  - House Joint Resolution No. 55 On the death of Alice Jackson Stuart (oversize) 2001 (Box 14)
  - The Justice George Lewis Ruffin Society, The Honorable Julian T. Houston, President 1985-1995 (Box 14)
  - Membership Cards of Alice Jackson Stuart ca. 1953-2000 (Box 14)
  - Memorabilia and Tickets for Events 1865, 1934-1999 (Box 14)
  - Memoranda Books ca. 1965-1978 (Box 14)
  - Memoranda Book, including some genealogical notes ca. 1982, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Menus 1957, n.d. (Box 14)
  - News clippings concerning Alice Jackson Stuart 1933-1998, n.d. (Box 14)
  - The Northern Student Movement, with Julian T. Houston as the representative from Boston University and Other Student Newsletters (2 folders) 1963-1966, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Obituaries and Funeral Programs (4 folders) 1956-2001, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Obituaries and Funeral Programs - Spottswood W. Robinson III, including later memorials and an earlier portrait presentation ceremony 1989, 1997-1999 (Box 15)
  - Photographs of Alice Jackson Stuart (passport) 1934, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Photograph of a group in front of American Medical Association Sign (oversize) n.d. (Box 15)
  - Photograph of the Delta Sigma Theta Annual Conclave, Cleveland, Ohio by Allen E. Cole (oversize) 1937 (Box 15)
  - Photographs - Identified or with captions (2 folders) ca. 1940-2001 (Box 15)
  - Photographs - Unidentified (2 folders) ca. 1950-1999 (Box 16)
  - Photographs - Negatives n.d. (Box 16)
  - Plaque - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Certificate of Life Membership of Alice Stuart - In Memoriam 1960 Jan (Box 16)
  - Plaque - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Certificate of Life Membership of J. Earle Stuart 1962 Feb (Box 16)
  - Plaque - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Certificate of Life Membership of Alice Jackson Stuart 1966 Jan (Box 16)
  - Plaque - Virginia Union University 50th Class Reunion 1984 Apr 28 (Box 16)
  - Posters of The United States National Student Association delegation to Japan, Hong Kong, Korea and lecture by Dr. Henry Louis Gates, Jr. at the Virginia Commonwealth University (oversize) 1967, 1987 (Box 16)
  - Programs - Art Functions 1954-1994, n.d. (Box 16)
  - Programs - Civil Rights Events and Related 1940-1998 (Box 17)
  - Programs - Concerts and Performances 1935-2000, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Programs - Dedication Ceremonies 1963-1994 (Box 17)
  - Programs - Educational Events and Commencements (2 folders) 1936-1999 (Box 17)
  - Programs - Literary Conferences and Events 1954-2001 (Box 17)
  - Programs -Political Events 1985-1995 (Box 17)
  - Programs - Religious 1955-1999 (Box 17)
  - Programs - Testimonials 1968-1997 (Box 17)
  - Programs - Weddings 1967-1999, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Recipes n.d. (Box 18)
  - Senate Joint Resolution No. 106 Offered January 23, 1990 Commending Alice Jackson Stuart 1990 (Box 18)
  - Senate Joint Resolution No. 40 On the death of Alice Jackson Stuart (oversize) 2001 (Box 18)
  - Slides, including West End Gardens Demolition Project, Tourism, Plainfield High School Graduation, "Galloping Hill," 920 East Front Street, John E. Runnells Hospital, etc. (2 folders) ca. 1956-1978, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - Awards, Honors, and Other Papers 1919-1981, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - Death and Estate of 1980-1989 (Box 18)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - Howard University Hospital 1974-1975 (Box 18)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - The Medical Society of New Jersey Meeting 1975 (Box 18)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - Photographs of Medical Work in New Jersey 1942, 1946, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - Scrapbook of Medical Work ca. 1940-1948, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Dr. James Earle Stuart - Wedding Book concerning his marriage to Alice Gertrude Taylor, with copy of the marriage service 1929 June 25 (Box 19)
  - Ethel Preston Tignor Family Tree 1978 (Box 19)
  - Travel - Africa and the Middle East 1962-1982 (Box 19)
  - Travel - Alaska 1983 (Box 19)
  - Travel - Austria 1965, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Travel - Canada ca. 1963-1966 (Box 19)
  - Travel - Caribbean Cruises ca. 1950-2000 (Box 19)
  - Travel - Denmark and Scandinavia ca. 1959-1965 (Box 20)
  - Travel - Diary of Dr. James Earle Stuart 1950 (Box 20)
  - Travel - Europe 1960-1985, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Travel - Great Britain 1977, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Travel - Italy and Switzerland 1964-1965 (Box 20)
  - Travel - Japan n.d. (Box 20)
  - Travel - New England n.d. (Box 20)
  - Travel - Postcards - Caribbean and African Culture n.d. (Box 20)
  - Travel - Puerto Rico 1959-1962 (Box 20)
  - Travel - West Indies Sunshine Cruise 1961 (Box 20)
  - Virginia Union University Commencement Program, including Alice Carlotta Jackson 1934 Jun 5 (Box 20)
  - Benjamin E. and Mary Grimshaw Washington 1942, 1957-1960, n.d. (Box 20)
- Series III: Notes and Writings by Alice Jackson Stuart (Box 20)
  - Book Reviews for Classes 1953, n. (Box 21)
  - "Communication and the Communication Arts," Teachers College, Columbia University 1952 (Box 21)
  - "Don Newcombe" - Manuscript and Notes (2 folders) ca. 1965 (Box 21)
  - "Don Newcombe" - Typescripts (2 folders) 1965 (Box 21)
  - "Don Newcombe" - Typescripts - Incomplete 1965 (Box 21)
  - "Don Newcombe" - Typescripts - Setting Copy 1966 (Box 21)
  - Essays by Alice Jackson Stuart, including one by James E. Jackson, Jr. 1954, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Essays and Papers written by Alice Jackson Stuart as a High School Student, formerly in a Three Ring Binder 1928-1930 (Box 21)
  - High School and College Essays and Papers by Alice Jackson Stuart 1929, n.d. (Box 22)
  - "Journey to Heaven" Television Adaptation of Mark Twain's Captain Stormfield's Visit to Heaven1953 (Box 22)
  - "Literary Criticism in John Milton's Prose Works" by Alice Carlotta Jackson, for M.A. degree, Columbia University (2 folders) 1939 Jun (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous Writings n.d. (Box 22)
  - "New Atlantis" by Francis Bacon, Script Adaptation for Instruction of Television Audiences 1953 (Box 22)
  - Newspaper Articles by Alice Jackson Stuart published in The Journal and Guide(3 folders) 1955-1956, n.d. (Box 22)
  - Notes concerning the Armed Forces Radio Service Seminar ca. 1954 (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning Black Literature and Culture n.d. (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning Geoffrey Chaucer n.d. (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning Communications 1967, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning John Dryden, Daniel Defoe, and Jonathan Swift 1937 (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning Educational Television ca. 1952-1954 (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning English Grammar n.d. (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning English Literature (2 folders) 1936, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning English Literature at Virginia Union University from classes of Arthur Paul Davis 1933-1934 (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning English Literature at Smith College 1935 (Box 23)
  - Notes concerning Henry Fielding Works 1937 (Box 24)
  - Notes concerning the Harlem Renaissance n.d. (Box 24)
  - Notes concerning Introduction to Medieval Literature 1936 (Box 24)
  - Notes concerning Literature Survey n.d. (Box 24)
  - Notes concerning John Milton (2 folders) 1936 (Box 24)
  - Notes concerning Miscellaneous Topics (3 folders) 1960, n.d. (Box 24)
  - Notes concerning Racial Relations n.d. (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Relationship of Religion in the schools and gifted students n.d. (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Seventeenth Century Literature (2 folders) 1934-1937 (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Seventeenth Century Literature at Columbia University [1937?] (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Shakespeare 1936 (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Edmund Spenser at Columbia University 1937 (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Teaching 1959, 1966, n.d. (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Teaching of English 1964, n.d. (Box 25)
  - Notes concerning Teaching of English n.d. (Box 26)
  - Notes concerning Teaching of Literature 1958, n.d. (Box 26)